<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philecoblog</title>
    <link>http://chreliot.github.io/philecoblog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on philecoblog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 12:14:19 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://chreliot.github.io/philecoblog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>One Philosophy of Science reading for an Evolution course</title>
      <link>http://chreliot.github.io/philecoblog/2015/07/one-reading-in-pos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chreliot.github.io/philecoblog/2015/07/one-reading-in-pos/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, the American Naturalist Society&amp;rsquo;s Twitter account (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ASNAmNat&#34;&gt;@ASNAmNat&lt;/a&gt;) retweeted a question posed by Daniel Bolnick (&lt;a href=&#34;!@t DanielBolnick&#34;&gt;@DanielBolnick&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can anyone recommend a good reading to teach intro evolution grad students about Philosophy of Science as it pertains to doing research?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is even a bit tougher request than, for example, a single reading introducing evolutionary biology or genetics. Philosophy of science is less unified than those disciplines. There aren&amp;rsquo;t many core consensus ideas for beginners to learn, with complexity gradually exposed to advanced students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-idea:ef8d8aae28d599820d4bc6b01db6b3b8&#34;&gt;One idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Bryan Roberts (&lt;a href=&#34;!@t SoulPhysics&#34;&gt;@SoulPhysics&lt;/a&gt;) tweeted a pretty good suggestion: Samir Okasha&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/title/philosophy-of-science-a-very-short-introduction/oclc/48932644&#34;&gt;Philosophy of Natural Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; from Oxford&amp;rsquo;s Very Short Introduction series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okasha&amp;rsquo;s introduction is very good. But I think it&amp;rsquo;s not ideal for serving as a single reading in a science course for students who won&amp;rsquo;t otherwise be exposed to Philosophy of Science. Trivially, at 134 pages, it&amp;rsquo;s not actually “Very Short.” I suspect it would push up against graduate students&amp;rsquo; attention spans. More significantly, it does something different than what I suggest a ideal single reading might do: it surveys the history of science, the history of Philosophy of Science, and a series of positions and debates and arguments at various levels of abstraction from science itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s left? Puzzles. I&amp;rsquo;d suggest that a good goal for quickly exposing science students to Philosophy of Science is to persuade them that genuinely compelling philosophical puzzles appear in the science they already know and in the reasoning behind it. Many science students reading or hearing about Philosophy of Science for the first time are skeptical that there could be anything to it, that it could amount to anything more than speculative blather dancing around the periphery of the established scientific facts. I want to persuade them otherwise, cultivate their eye for recognizing philosophical problems in their own work and disciplines, and ideally communicate that a large literature on such problems exists. Most of all, I want them to go from zero to “Hmmm, wow, I don&amp;rsquo;t know, and I would have thought I did,” as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t mean that Okasha fails to present questions, problems, and open debates. I mean that in that short book he favors a more systematic presentation over foregrounding particular puzzling problems and what makes them difficult and exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-suggestion:ef8d8aae28d599820d4bc6b01db6b3b8&#34;&gt;My suggestion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I suggest for the Evolution class is “What is the principle of natural selection?” Don&amp;rsquo;t start with that question. On its own, is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a compelling question for most students. So let&amp;rsquo;s get there in two readings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First reading: Carl Hempel, &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Natural Science&lt;/em&gt; (1966), pages 47–58 in the chapter “Laws and Their Role in Scientific Explanation.” (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/title/philosophy-of-natural-science/oclc/396051&amp;amp;amp;referer=brief_results &amp;quot;Philosophy of natural science (Book, 1966&#34;&gt;Worldcat link&lt;/a&gt; [WorldCat.org]&amp;ldquo;)) Hempel argues that laws are an essential part of scientific theories, in that only they can ground explanatory understanding. Pump students&amp;rsquo; intuitions by discussing Newton&amp;rsquo;s laws and the Ideal Gas Law. Newton&amp;rsquo;s achievement was identifying several laws that work together to explain extremely diverse phenomena. Hempel argues that such laws must be true, universal generalizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second reading: John Beatty, “The Evolutionary Contingency Thesis.” in &lt;em&gt;Concepts, Theories, and Rationality in the Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Gereon Wolters and James G. Lennox, 45–81. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1995. (Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/wcpa/oclc/32818943?page=frame&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fdigital.library.pitt.edu%2Fcgi-bin%2Ft%2Ftext%2Ftext-idx%3Fc%3Dpittpress%3Bview%3Dtoc%3Bidno%3D31735060482415%26checksum%3D9cc497770fae70c06e7e9bea3929c94d&amp;amp;title=&amp;amp;linktype=digitalObject&amp;amp;detail=&#34; title=&#34;Evolutionary Contingency Thesis&#34;&gt;Worldcat listing&lt;/a&gt; for the book, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/text-idx?c=pittpress;view=toc;idno=31735060482415&#34;&gt;a digital copy&lt;/a&gt; from Pittsburgh Press.) Beatty argues in an accessible way that since biological organisms have evolved in contingent ways, any distinctly biological law-like generalizations must be contingent on that evolutionary history, rather than universally true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think students reading those should start to be puzzled about at least some of the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the principle of natural selection? Can it be expressed a law, like one of Newton&amp;rsquo;s laws? If we try to express it as a law, is the result true? Is natural selection instead a historical process, or a mechanism, or a metaphor characterizing a model of organic change, or what? Does biology have any other laws? Does evolutionary biology make predictions? Must scientific theories be capable of making predictions? What makes evolutionary theory a scientific theory if it fails have a law of natural selection? What counts as an explanation in evolutionary biology, if not logical deduction from laws and circumstances? What&amp;rsquo;s the relationship between the theory of evolutionary biology and the theories in Chemistry and Physics? And more specifically, is Gould right that evolution could have played out differently, in nearly infinite ways? In what ways are other possibilities possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students can zero in on the specific questions they find most puzzling. This pair of readings raises other questions. There are a lot. I think if students find themselves genuinely puzzled by any of these questions—with doubt about how to answer them combined with a sense that they should have clear answers—the assignment succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certainly other readings and pairs of readings that could accomplish the same thing. This is just the first one that struck me as good for a graduate Evolution course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emerging Philosophy of Ecology at ISHPSSB 2015</title>
      <link>http://chreliot.github.io/philecoblog/2015/07/ishpssb2015-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2015 12:28:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chreliot.github.io/philecoblog/2015/07/ishpssb2015-recap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was delighted how much work in Philosophy of Ecology was presented at this year&amp;rsquo;s biennial &lt;a href=&#34;https://ishpssb2015.uqam.ca/&#34;&gt;meeting in Montréal&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://ishpssb.org/&#34; title=&#34;ISHPSSB&#34;&gt;ISHPSSB&lt;/a&gt;, the International Society for History, Philosophy, and Social Studies of Biology. It was the largest ISH so far, far larger than when I started attending 15 years ago, with about 550 presenters and 650 participants. The attendees also felt far more international than in years past, and represented 35 different countries. The presentations skewed heavily toward Philosophy this year, rather than History or Sociology/Anthropology, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t see any History of Ecology presented by historians this time. Yet presentations by biologists and at least one social scientist blended seamlessly into the Philosophy of Science-dominated sessions I attended, realizing one of the ambitions of ISH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a recap of the Philosophy of Ecology presentations I attended:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophy.fsu.edu/content/view/full/35712&#34; title=&#34;- Florida State University Department of Philosophy&#34;&gt;Jack Justus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Florida State Univ., philosophy professor), who&amp;rsquo;s been writing in Philosophy of Ecology for some time, gave close attention to the various versions of the niche concept as they emerged in Ecology. Joseph Grinnell&amp;rsquo;s focus was on environmental space (a more biogeographical concept) and Charles Elton&amp;rsquo;s was on biotic interactions (a more community-oriented concept). But it&amp;rsquo;s a mistake, Jack observed, to think Elton had no focus on the abiotic factors Grinnell emphasized, even as he treated them as much less important. Since &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; ecologists recognized vacant niches, whatever individuates niches is unclear on the Grinnell-Elton concept. Meanwhile, Richard Lewontin held that empty niches aren&amp;rsquo;t coherent, and for Georgii Gause they were just K–N (which is to say the quantitative gap between population sizes and carrying capacity). Not only is there a multiplicity of meanings for “niche,” but also the various associated concepts have been described in confused ways. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to this paper, or—Jack proposed—this book!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zoology.ubc.ca/person/kmarshall&#34; title=&#34;Katie Marshall at The Department of Zoology at the University of British Columbia&#34;&gt;Katie Marshall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of British Columbia, zoology postdoctoral fellow) presented philosophically-interesting ideas based on her lab&amp;rsquo;s entomology research. She contrasted top-down and bottom-up modeling approaches, and suggested that top-down models of the realized niche may be vulnerable to novel conditions including climate change. Specifically, plasticity, variable limits of tolerance, limits of tolerance defined by sensitivity to threshold-crossing events rather than absolute values, and the influence of microclimates all make niches more complex. Beyond its implications for modeling in the face of a shifting climate, this argument was especially interesting for me because my &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.6959004.0003.001&#34; title=&#34;Competition Theory and Channeling Explanation&#34;&gt;2011 paper&lt;/a&gt; on channeling explanations in Ecology assumed that we can identify hard limits for population viability, and I need to think more about whether plasticity and the other circumstances Katie described create a problem for that. Also, Alkistis (below), a philosopher who has been in the same lab as Katie, recruited her to present, and it was very welcome to have a biologist presenting on philosophical issues in Ecology at ISH.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://acdussault.profweb.ca/en/&#34;&gt;Antoine Dussaault&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of Montréal, philosophy graduate student) built on the  suggestion I&amp;rsquo;ve made (&lt;a href=&#34;http://people.hofstra.edu/Christopher_H_Eliot/Eliot2007postprint.pdf&#34; title=&#34;PDF&#34;&gt;2007&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.hofstra.edu/Christopher_H_Eliot/Eliot2011Legend-web.pdf&#34; title=&#34;PDF&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;) about the polarization of early 20th-century plant ecologists Frederic Clements and Henry Gleason, which I&amp;rsquo;ve objected to and called “the legend of Order and Chaos.” My reading bringing them closer together in turn built on Joel Hagen&amp;rsquo;s (1988) take on Clements and Malcolm Nicolson&amp;rsquo;s (2002) take on Gleason (though I read them near the end of formulating it, and so consider it a case of happy convergence). I had downplayed Clements&amp;rsquo;s and Gleason&amp;rsquo;s metaphysical commitments, especially the degree to which Clements believed ecological communities exist as real, bounded objects, similar in structure to familiar macro-organisms. Antoine argued that Clements&amp;rsquo;s metaphysical commitments are stronger than I&amp;rsquo;d allowed. Using historical context, Antoine analyzed the gap between Clements and Gleason as widened by the new understanding of what it is to be an organism introduced by the neo-Darwinian synthesis of the 1930s and 40s. The emerging understanding of “organisms” as gene-vehicles conflicted with Clements&amp;rsquo;s understanding of organisms on a more Lamarckian model left over from late 19th Century biology, and that&amp;rsquo;s a big part of what Gleason was responding to, Antoine argued. I do wonder if the timeline works out here, but this is an intriguing suggestion!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://alkistis-elliott-graves.squarespace.com/&#34;&gt;Alkistis Elliott-Graves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Western University, postdoctoral fellow in philosophy) presented in the same session. She&amp;rsquo;s interested in why prediction is challenging in Ecology. She suggested that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/27836590&#34; title=&#34;JSTOR&#34;&gt;Levins 1966&lt;/a&gt; makes too much of complexity and too little of causal heterogeneity as problems for prediction. Her larger project is reevaluating what kind of predictions should be the goal in Ecology, specifically whether more local, temporally proximate, qualitative predictions offer appropriate targets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophy.umn.edu/people/profile.php?UID=bausm007&#34; title=&#34;William Bausman : Philosophy : University of Minnesota&#34;&gt;Will Bausman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of Minnesota, philosophy graduate student) has been working on the foundations of the Neutral Theory of Biodiversity (Hubbell 2001). Will critiqued Hubbell&amp;rsquo;s own story about what events and reason led him to articulating the Neutral Theory. A Will puts it, “One persistent epistemological question asks how the neutral theory can be useful given its `obviously false&amp;rsquo; assumption that all individuals in a community are functionally equivalent. I believe asking this question is prompted by a particular narrative about the origin and development of the Neutral Theory—the origin story Stephen Hubbell, its chief innovator, tells.” In characterizing some epistemological debates about the Neutral Theory, Will suggested, among other things, that ecologists discussing the Neutral Theory have often not been clear about the distinctions between null models and null hypotheses, and between null models and baseline models. Whereas null models offer default explanations, for instance, null hypotheses suggest there&amp;rsquo;s no explanation to be had. This is part of his evolving dissertation work focused on the Neutral Theory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anu-au.academia.edu/ChristopherLean&#34; title=&#34;Christopher Lean | The Australian National University - Academia.edu&#34;&gt;Chris Lean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Australian National Univ., philosophy graduate student) organized a session with Roberta Millstien and me titled “What Are Ecological Communities, and Are They Preservable?” Chris&amp;rsquo;s paper built on Kim Sterelny&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://philpapers.org/rec/KIMLEC&#34; title=&#34;Kim Sterelny, Local Ecological Communities - PhilPapers&#34;&gt;2006 discussion&lt;/a&gt; of indexical communities—communities which can be identified relative to individual, focal populations. I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; he thinks indexical communities are &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way to understand communities. While (following Ricklefs et al.) local patches lack persistent species identity, in indexical communities non-additive, emergent properties are everywhere, he observed. I&amp;rsquo;ll be interested to see how he develops the idea of an indexical community beyond Sterelny&amp;rsquo;s brief treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the same session on communities, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://home.comcast.net/~rmillstein1/&#34; title=&#34;Roberta L. Millstein&#34;&gt;Roberta Millstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of Calif. at Davis, professor of philosophy) focused specifically on Aldo Leopold&amp;rsquo;s “land community” concept. Leopold often referred to the “biotic community,” but idiosyncratically included land, soil, water, and such as components. Roberta is investigating what questions are involved in assessing whether the land community can be an object of direct moral obligation, as Leopold suggested it is. She analyzed how well the concept make senses across a series of cases of open systems. In both her project and Chris Lean&amp;rsquo;s, there&amp;rsquo;s an intersection where Philosophy of Ecology can do important work, I think, figuring out what it is that projects in areas like Environmental Ethics need, in relation to what Ecology offers, or could offer. Ecologists describe all sorts of communities, but are there any communities of the sort environmental ethicists want there to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also in that session, I recapped and built on the interest-relative-but-real concept of communities I argued for briefly at the end of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.hofstra.edu/Christopher_H_Eliot/Eliot2011Legend-web.pdf&#34; title=&#34;PDF&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.hofstra.edu/Christopher_H_Eliot/Eliot2013Objects.pdf&#34; title=&#34;Eliot 2013 PDF&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/a&gt; papers. I think one kind important kind of ecological community is a function of interest in a particular kind of causation like dependance or competition. Such communities are not as ontologically robust—not so strongly observer-independent in their status as objects—as communities defined by emergent properties are, which are one sort Sterelny has characterized. I recommended that to the extent any objects are defined by emergent causal properties, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; overlapping objects are so defined, such that emergent properties don&amp;rsquo;t work to pick out stronger communities than the interest-relative ones I&amp;rsquo;ve previously argued for. There are some loose ends on this account that need tying up, though, and the audience did a good job of picking some of them out!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sfu.ca/philosophy/people/faculty/profiles/holly-andersen.html&#34;&gt;Holly Andersen&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Simon Fraser University, Philosophy professor) presentation in “Authors Meet Critics: &lt;em&gt;In Search of Mechanisms&lt;/em&gt; (2013)”—a session on philosophers Lindley Darden and Carl Craver&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/title/in-search-of-mechanisms-discoveries-across-the-life-sciences/oclc/826899648&#34;&gt;recent book&lt;/a&gt;—reflected on how ecosystems are interesting systems for evaluating claims about mechanisms, in so far as individual ecosystems are quite particular in structure, and it&amp;rsquo;s challenging to generalize across them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marion Durand&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of Toronto, graduate student) presented a defence of statistical explanations in Ecology and evolutionary theory, arguing against those like Rosenberg who&amp;rsquo;ve suggested that merely statistical explanations aren&amp;rsquo;t actually explanatory. Hers was one of the sessions that impressed me that some of the most exciting and best-presented work at the meeting was offered by graduate students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stephanie Meirmans&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of Leiden, Biology graduate student, I think) paper “Scientific Methods in Ecology and Evolution” explored how observation, experimentation, and theory mutually reinforce one another in those disciplines, though unfortunately she didn&amp;rsquo;t have time in the presentation to apply the ideas to specifically ecological examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ufv.ca/scms/faculty-and-staff/faculty-members/faculty-members/faculty-and-staffchantelle-marlor/&#34;&gt;Chantelle Marlor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of the Fraser Valley, sociology faculty) argued that increasing recognition of animal culture has interesting implications for models in community Ecology. She&amp;rsquo;s continuing to work on ways animal culture might affect specific models. I realized that I don&amp;rsquo;t know the extent to which that connection has already been made by modelers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://univ-paris1.academia.edu/SebastienDutreuil&#34;&gt;Sebastien Dutreuil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Université Paris 1,  Panthéon-Sorbonne, philosophy graduate student) won the conference&amp;rsquo;s best poster prize for his poster, “What Philosophy of Biology Got Wrong on the Gaia Hypothesis.” He argued that while most of the criticism of the Gaia Hypothesis was in the context of evolutionary biology, the hypothesis was “not just a metaphor, and did not aim to contribute to evolutionary biology.” Sebastien suggests it makes more sense understood, as he thinks it was intended by Lovelock, as a geophysical hypothesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsci.uc.edu/faculty-staff/listing/by_dept/philosophy.html?eid=rogerseg&#34; title=&#34;Philosophy, University of Cincinnati&#34;&gt;Eric Rogers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Univ. of Cincinnati, philosophy graduate student) is analyzing the terminological disunity in Invasion Biology. He thinks variation in usage has confounded research integration, impeded effective management, and produced conflicting messages to the public about invasions, invasion biology, and its goals. Beyond working on conceptual clarification, Eric suggested that biologists consider the needs and demands of non-biologist collaborators as part of resolving terminology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was also a session on “De-Extinction” and rewilding with &lt;strong&gt;Markku Oksanen&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Helena Siipi&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Derek Turner&lt;/strong&gt;, though the talks concentrated on the ways the possibility of de-extinction complicates the circumstances under which we can say a species is extinct, rather than on anything specifically ecological. Still, is a reconstructed mammoth actually a mammoth if it&amp;rsquo;s missing most of a mammoth&amp;rsquo;s ecological relationships?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, there was a lot of interesting work. Furthermore, I missed a paper by &lt;strong&gt;Georg Toepfer&lt;/strong&gt; (Zentrum für Literatur und Kulturforschung, professor) I would have liked to attend, intriguingly titled “Philosophy of Ecology Long Before Ecology: Kant’s Idea of an Organized System of Organized Beings.” His abstract suggests I&amp;rsquo;ll want to read his article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a distinct biological subdiscipline, Ecology did not emerge before the beginning of the twentieth century. But its underlying conceptual framework was developed long before. Important organizing ideas emerged within the physicotheological tradition of the eighteenth century, for example, with Carl Linnaeus’ concept of an “economy of nature” or the related idea of an interconnecting “nexus” between the organisms of different species. In the last years of his life, Immanuel Kant elaborated on these ideas and provided concise formulations and conceptual models for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other philosophers who&amp;rsquo;ve written about ecology were present at ISH and attended a lot of the sessions, but didn&amp;rsquo;t present on ecology per se. They included: &lt;strong&gt;Jay Odenbaugh&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Greg Mikkelson&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Sahotra Sarkar&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Kim Sterelny&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Bill Wimsatt&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Peter Taylor&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Eric Desjardins&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Michael Weisberg&lt;/strong&gt;, and one of the local co-hosts of this very well-organized meeting, &lt;strong&gt;Frédéric Bouchard&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a good time to work on Philosophy of Ecology!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>